<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Lyza Danger Gardner: life]]></title><description><![CDATA[Developer and Person]]></description><link>http://www.lyza.com</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Mar 2018 16:23:39 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://www.lyza.com/feeds/life.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Mar 2018 16:23:37 GMT</pubDate><language><![CDATA[en-US]]></language><managingEditor><![CDATA[Lyza Danger Gardner]]></managingEditor><webMaster><![CDATA[Lyza Danger Gardner]]></webMaster><item><title><![CDATA[And now for something completely&#8230;different?]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Up until a few months ago, I lived in a space-constrained duplex in a happening urban neighborhood in happening Portland, Oregon. Now I live in the middle of a mountainous forest in Vermont, on a dirt road, next to a river. I changed jobs. I got rid of about 75% of what I owned. On the face of it, everything has changed. Or has it?</p>
<p>Here are some thoughts on all of the changes, as well as some thoughts on how much hasn’t changed at all. In the form of a FAQ, because: why not?</p>
<h2 id="wait-where-exactly-do-you-live-now-">Wait. Where exactly do you live now?</h2>
<p>In a town in southern Vermont. When I say <em>town</em>, I mean it in the New England sense: a square-ish area of land roughly 6 to 10 miles on a side. Not all towns have villages or any form of conurbation; ours does but it is about eight miles distant.</p>
<p>We live on a dirt road that is well-maintained but is, still, dirt. Our nearest neighbors are across the river, about 800 feet as the crow flies but a quarter-mile walk to get there. They’re the only neighbors within screaming distance.</p>
<h2 id="where-the-heck-do-you-buy-food-and-stuff-">Where the heck do you buy food and stuff?</h2>
<p>There’s a general store about six-and-a-half minutes away by car. The two local villages are each about a 12-minute drive. One has a grocery store I’d roughly equate to Safeway on the west coast: it’s sufficient but not inspiring.</p>
<p>It’s remarkable and rewarding how much of our food is obtained directly from the humans who made it. We belong to a little CSA up the road—it’s personal enough that they’ll notice and comment on our absence if they don’t see us for a week or two. There’s a Jersey dairy—raw milk and eggs—down the road. Pork and chicken often comes from another farm run by a couple in the next town over. And one of our neighbors raises grass-fed lamb (and may—CROSS FINGERS—scale into acorn-fed pork soon).</p>
<h2 id="what-s-the-landscape-like-">What’s the landscape like?</h2>
<p>Tons of local relief. Our house is at the bottom of a valley. We are surrounded by forest, save for a small field on the east end of our property which is used for hay for our neighbor’s sheep. I usually say that, aside from that field, you can tell when you’re on our property because you won’t be able to stand up properly—it’s that steep, most of it.</p>
<p>There’s a river. Technically it’s the North Branch of the Williams River, but no one ever calls it that. It’s just <em>the river</em>. It’s a small river; you can walk across it easily, a large creek, really. The water is clear and the rocks various and interesting.</p>
<h2 id="so-you-re-off-grid-or-whatever-">So, you’re off-grid or whatever?</h2>
<p>No, not entirely. So, no. We do have a grid-tied pole-mounted 3kW solar array, but it doesn’t power the whole house. We’re also connected to civilization through our phone/Internet lines (more on that shortly). Aside from that, though, yes: we have a well, septic. Our heating fuel is provided by an in-ground propane tank.</p>
<h2 id="getting-online-must-suck-">Getting online must suck?</h2>
<p>Is that a question or a statement? Here’s the best part of all the parts, when taken as part of the beautiful whole: our Internet is <em>fantastic</em>. The local telecom got a grant from the federal government and used it to invest in a fiber grid. We pay a reasonable amount and we get reliable 1G symmetric connectivity (real-world performance between 600-800Mbps). Yee haw!</p>
<h2 id="aren-t-you-terribly-isolated-">Aren’t you terribly isolated?</h2>
<p>This has been the most surprising thing about this change. I expected to have loneliness, to have to work intensely to have contact with other humans. And yet. We know all of our neighbors. Our front yard and porch are visible from the road and sometimes people just drop by if they see us. Our friends and family visit us.</p>
<p>Sometimes we won’t leave our property for four or five days at a stretch and it isn’t bothersome at all.</p>
<h2 id="so-you-work-from-home-">So you work from home?</h2>
<p>Yep! I’m lucky to have my position as an Open Web Engineer at Bocoup. Their systems and people are well-oriented for distributed teams. We’re fortunate to have a real, dedicated office portion of our house: a separate staircase, large shared office room and a half-bathroom. So “going to work” feels like a thing, still.</p>
<h2 id="and-you-re-not-going-crazy-">And you’re not going crazy?</h2>
<p>Nope.</p>
<h2 id="really-">Really?</h2>
<p>Really. But we’ll see what happens once winter comes!</p>
]]></description><link>http://www.lyza.com/2016/09/20/and-now-for-something-completelydifferent/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.lyza.com/2016/09/20/and-now-for-something-completelydifferent/</guid><category><![CDATA[life]]></category><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2016 17:38:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Lyza&#8217;s Index: September/October Rundown]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>The past month has been blurry, due, in part, to some health fun I’ll gloss over here. But before I’m off again (it’s travel season), I wanted to jot down a few highlights.</p>
<h2 id="tech">Tech</h2>
<h3 id="responsive-field-day-cloud-four-s-first-conference-">Responsive Field Day: Cloud Four’s first conference!</h3>
<p>For <a href="http://www.cloudfour.com">Cloud Four</a> staff, <a href="http://www.responsivefieldday.com">Responsive Field Day</a> was a big ol’ deal, one of the bigger things about our 2015 so far. Everything I have to say about the quality of the talks, the community feel of the event, and the contributions of Cloud Four-ians is so laudatory that it doesn’t leave much else in my brain. Maybe that’s part of being so close to the planning and execution of it. Maybe I can’t see the proverbial forest for the trees. But, as well, all of the feedback I’ve received has been emphatically positive. So, I don’t know. It seemed, just…<em>damned good</em>.</p>
<p>It was the first event Cloud Four has put on, and the first event for which I was deeply involved in planning. I enjoyed the hell out of it.</p>
<p>You can find videos and podcast-ed audio of everything from the day, talks and panels, on the <a href="http://www.responsivefieldday.com">event’s web site</a>.</p>
<p><img src="win-goodbody-photo.jpg" alt="Hosting a panel about progressive enhancement at Responsive Field Day"></p>
<p><em>Photo copyright 2015 <a href="http://www.wingoodbody.photography/Event/20150925-Responsive-Field-Day/i-PzCzdDb">Win Goodbody</a></em></p>
<h3 id="writings-on-service-workers-and-progressive-enhancement">Writings: On Service Workers and Progressive Enhancement</h3>
<p>My <a href="http://alistapart.com/column/how-do-we-get-it-done-now">column this month</a> for <em>A List Apart</em> struck a nerve! On the good side, it’s kicked up some good conversation about how to get things done to make offline-first a reality, <em>now</em>. For example, <a href="http://davidwalsh.name/dont-wait-serviceworker-adding-offline-support-oneline">David Walsh from Surge explains a tool for managinge App Cache more simply</a>.</p>
<p>The Web is complex and fun and I hope we keep making it the best we can.</p>
<h2 id="non-tech">Non-tech</h2>
<h3 id="on-british-village-names-">On British village names…</h3>
<p>A habit I’ve had since I was about ten is poring over maps the way someone else might read novels. I was in Wales a few years ago, whiling away a country evening flipping through a British driving atlas when I started to obsess over how wonderful British village names can be. I’m going to save diving into this until later, because it absolutely deserves its own post, but the esteemed Chris Higgins used an early spreadsheet I made of some of the choice finds to inspire a recent <a href="http://mentalfloss.com/article/69445/43-charmingly-odd-british-town-names">article on Mental Floss</a>.</p>
<h3 id="on-the-domestic-front-">On the domestic front…</h3>
<p>Here’s proof that I can Pinterest with the rest of ‘em. I got bored with the scraped-up crappy melamine top of the rolling coffee table in the living room (Ikea, and how).</p>
<h4 id="before">Before</h4>
<p><img src="before.jpg" alt="Stupid Table: Before"></p>
<h4 id="then">Then</h4>
<p>Sanding, priming, and gold spray paint.</p>
<h4 id="after">After</h4>
<p><img src="after-1.jpg" alt="Stupid Table: After"></p>
<p><img src="after-2.jpg" alt="Stupid Table: After 2"></p>
]]></description><link>http://www.lyza.com/2015/10/16/lyzas-index-septemberoctober-rundown/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.lyza.com/2015/10/16/lyzas-index-septemberoctober-rundown/</guid><category><![CDATA[life]]></category><category><![CDATA[til]]></category><pubDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2015 20:33:55 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Time for a New Project]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>It’s an awkward time of the year. People with little ones are pushing them back toward school buses. The weather is doing something transitional. Vim held strong when entering the season faded into a mild flatness by the end of it.</p>
<h2 id="a-quick-summer-retrospective">A Quick Summer Retrospective</h2>
<p>July and August were cerebral for me. I managed to ship <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cz6EUrXizXo">my video about life and springtime</a>, I read a dozen or so books, and, ultimately, coded <a href="http://www.lyza.com">this site</a> from scratch, but I’m left feeling as if I have little of interest to show to anyone outside of my own head.</p>
<h2 id="and-now-for-something-completely-different-">And Now for Something…Completely Different?</h2>
<p>It’s time for something new, something forward. I’ve been on a hobby moratorium for a few years, out of guilt for my languishing pre-existing ones, but maybe it’s time to shrug off that mantle and get excited about something new. Any ideas?</p>
]]></description><link>http://www.lyza.com/2015/09/02/time-for-a-new-project/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.lyza.com/2015/09/02/time-for-a-new-project/</guid><category><![CDATA[projects]]></category><category><![CDATA[life]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 02 Sep 2015 17:24:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Lyza&#8217;s Index: Alaska Edition]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Last weekend, I went to Alaska. I don’t know why it took me so long—it’s been almost five years since I went to my last new state (Hawaii). In fact, Alaska makes a cool 50—I’ve been to ‘em all now.</p>
<h3 id="sea-canaries">Sea canaries</h3>
<p>Turnagain Arm is a dead-end, long finger of sea extending eastward from Anchorage off of Cook Inlet. We drove around it to get to the Kenai Peninsula.</p>
<p>Cook Inlet—including Turnagain Arm—has a population of Beluga whales. Most of the world’s population of Belugas is more arctic, and the Cook Inlet Belugas are genetically isolated. DNA suggests no inter-breeding with other Belugas for something like 6000 years. Unfortunately, about half of the Cook Inlet Belugas died off mysteriously in the 1990s and the herd (pod?) is still struggling to slowly re-establish itself. So I feel doubly lucky that I was able to spot a few, just white humps, out in the water on this trip. Who knows how long they’ll be around? (Source for this: various interpretive signs at Beluga Point and Bird Point along the Seward Highway. I have a generally-reliable memory, but this is non-robust, source-wise).</p>
<p>Belugas are one of my favorite whales (perhaps only beaten out by narwhals, which are amazing). They have this lovely demeanor and they look like they’d be good friends. I <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beluga_whale">learned by watching Wikipedia</a> that they are sometimes called <em>Sea Canaries</em> because of their “high-pitched twitter”. And also, through associated Wiki-drift, that echolocation and such elaborate chatter are restricted to whales that have teeth (Odontoceti).</p>
<h3 id="other-things-waterbound">Other Things Waterbound</h3>
<p>We also saw a sea otter in the harbor at Seward. I’ve been reading <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Alaska-Novel-James-A-Michener/dp/037576142X">James Michener’s <em>Alaska</em></a>, which has a goodly amount to say about sea otters, so I wasn’t taken by surprise by how big she or he was. He or she was big! And relaxed, swimming on his/her back and grooming and pausing to let us take photos and video. Did you know that sea otters have the densest fur of any animal? (Both roadsign park signs <em>and</em> <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sea_otter">Wikipedia</a> agree on that <em>so it must be true</em>.)</p>
<p>Late August is spawning season for silver salmon on the Kenai peninsula, and we timidly peered into solid creeks of flipping, disintegrating fish, nervously scanning around for salmon-keen bears.</p>
<p>We were ill-timed (being mid-moon-cycle) and so weren’t able to see the legendary <a href="http://www.alaska.org/advice/alaska-bore-tide">bore tide in Turnagain Arm</a>, but I, fascinated with tides in general, console myself by the claim that (from highway signs!) the bore tide hasn’t been nearly as amazing since the 1964 Good Friday earthquake dropped the entire arm’s seafloor by about six feet. The magnitude-9.3 quake put a number of communities (Portage, Girdwood, Hope) partially or completely under flood. They moved Girdwood up the mountain a couple of miles. They gave up on Portage entirely. Hope starts further inland now, the former water-frontage streets now part of the sea.</p>
<h3 id="late-summer-trip-perks">Late-summer Trip Perks</h3>
<p>Flights and crowds in Alaska in the summer are usually painfully expensive and painfully present, respectively. However, we seem to have found a loophole. Maybe it was fare wars between Alaska Airlines and JetBlue, but round-trip flights in August to Anchorage from Portland could be had for as little as $157. And since we opted to camp, Anchorage’s seizure-inducing lodging prices were mostly avoided other than the $275 or so we had to drop on an airport Holiday Inn Express because our flight (cheap, but…) landed at 2:00 AM. The return flight was also oddly-timed, leaving at nearly 1:00 AM, but on the flip side, I got to stare, ecstatic, at 90 minutes or the northern lights through my window, pale green and beautiful.</p>
<p>I recommend visiting this part of Alaska in late August—it’s still summer, but the locals are all starting to talk about how winter is coming. The aspens are just starting to go gold (though the alders are still summer-leafed) and the crowds seem to have tapered a little. I’d also like to tout that I didn’t get a single bug bite—another benefit of the later season. Camping on the Kenai is pleasant and easy, not bush wilderness but accessible landscape, landscape far bigger than average.</p>
]]></description><link>http://www.lyza.com/2015/08/30/lyzas-index-alaska-edition/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.lyza.com/2015/08/30/lyzas-index-alaska-edition/</guid><category><![CDATA[life]]></category><category><![CDATA[til]]></category><pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2015 20:34:23 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Lyza&#8217;s Index: July 30]]></title><description><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aerogel">Aerogel</a> is so not-dense that it’s hard to see the edges of it, which tend to diffuse into nothingness subtly. (for more, read: <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Stuff-Matters-Exploring-Marvelous-Materials/dp/0544236041"><em>Stuff Matters: Exploring the Marvelous Materials that Shape our Man-Made World</em></a> )</li>
<li>In Naples, there are DOC-designated pizzas. If you make a margherita pizza with the wrong kind of tomatoes or mozzarella, you’re not in the club.</li>
<li>Perhaps Charles Lindbergh’s greatest feat in his first transatlantic flight was that he found the airfield in Paris after flying from New York using <em>dead reckoning</em>. Imagine that. (for more, read: <a href="http://www.amazon.com/One-Summer-America-Bill-Bryson-ebook/dp/B00C8S9VKM/ref=sr_1_4?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1438297354&amp;sr=1-4&amp;keywords=bill+bryson"><em>One Summer: America, 1927</em></a> )</li>
</ul>
<p>The following is nifty ES6/JS 2015 goodness:</p>
<pre><code class="lang-javascript"><span class="hljs-class"><span class="hljs-keyword">class</span> <span class="hljs-title">Whatever</span> </span>{
  <span class="hljs-keyword">constructor</span>({
    foo = <span class="hljs-string">'bar'</span>,
    baz = <span class="hljs-string">'bing'</span>
  } = {}) {
    <span class="hljs-comment">// Yeah, baby</span>
    <span class="hljs-built_in">console</span>.log(foo); <span class="hljs-comment">// =&gt; 'bar' by default</span>
  }
}
</code></pre>
<p>Hat-tip to <a href="https://twitter.com/tylersticka">@tylersticka</a> on that one!</p>
]]></description><link>http://www.lyza.com/2015/07/30/lyzas-index-july-30/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.lyza.com/2015/07/30/lyzas-index-july-30/</guid><category><![CDATA[life]]></category><category><![CDATA[til]]></category><pubDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2015 23:12:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Rajneeshees: Another Sign I am a Portland Native]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>My co-workers highlighted <a href="http://digg.com/video/rajneeshee-bioterror-attack-dalles-oregon-taco-time-salsa">this recent video on digg</a>, part of a series entitled “Atlas Obscura” (thus, presumably denoting its informational contents are, well, obscure), about the salad-bar poisoning by the Rajneeshees in The Dalles, Oregon in 1984.</p>
<p>Except this information, to me, is anything but obscure. In my memory, the Rajneesh situation flavored several years of Oregon culture and news reporting. My mom still occasionally references it in casual conversation.</p>
<p>It made me curious: How many people know of this event? Is it really so banished to the obscure edges of history? Is it just a sign that I’m getting old, and/or that I am hopelessly <em>from Oregon</em> in that entrenched way? Do I already sound like I’m my porch rocking chair, creaking on about how <em>In my day, cults poisoned salad bars?</em></p>
]]></description><link>http://www.lyza.com/2015/07/28/the-rajneeshees-another-sign-i-am-a-portland-native/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.lyza.com/2015/07/28/the-rajneeshees-another-sign-i-am-a-portland-native/</guid><category><![CDATA[oregon]]></category><category><![CDATA[life]]></category><pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2015 18:45:01 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>